07:02PM
on 05/04/2020.
This is the meeting of the Town of Andover Inland Wetlands and Water Forces Commission.
I'm gonna read the standard virtual meeting intro that we read last time. So this is a web based call. So we're operating under the following procedures and I should introduce myself. I'm sorry. I'm Megan Lally. I'm the chairman of the Inland Wetlands and Waterforce Commission.
So
this session is being audio recorded, just like every other Inland Wetlands and Water Forces Commission meeting.
And please be advised that today we are also recording the video of the proceedings.
To ensure sound quality, the default rule for this meeting is that everyone will remain on mute. Commissioners and staff will generally remain on mute except when speaking or voting, keeping
video of themselves on throughout the meeting.
Applicants and members of the public should feel free to leave their video on or off. However, you will be asked to turn on your video when speaking if possible. If video is not available for you, you're not going to be precluded from speaking or providing public testimony.
If you are speaking at this meeting and have materials to submit to the commission, which were not distributed in advance of the meeting with the rest of the materials, please indicate that you wish to submit a document. You'll need to hold it up to the camera so that the commission and all members of the public may review it. In addition, you will be required to email the document or take a photograph of it and email it to buildingadminandoverct
dot org,
and we will include it in the permanent records of the commission.
Please note that this is not a public hearing. There are no public hearings scheduled tonight.
Members of the public may only speak during an open public hearing. If a member of the public creates an audio or video disruption,
they may be manually ejected from the meeting upon recommendation of staff or the chair. Hopefully, will not happen.
With that,
we'll move on to item two on the agenda, roll call in seating of alternates.
Megan Lowley, chair, is present.
George Elliott, vice chair,
is present.
Jed Larson,
Commission Member and Planning and Zoning Representative,
is present.
Jim Halsey, Commissioner, is present but serving as Wetlands Agent for this meeting.
I do not see Commissioner Ed Smith
on the call.
Correct?
Okay. So no Ed tonight.
And then, alternate Wayne Thorpe does not appear to be on the call either. Alright.
So we will continue with the quorum.
>> Item three, are there any additions or changes in order to the agenda?
Jed, George, or Jim?
Or I guess not Jim. I had the
But I'll
make a motion. Jed or George, did you have anything you wanted to add or remove or change?
No changes.
>> Okay,
I
did want to add under
topic six, permit applications,
a new item D.
We have a pre permit application
regarding 26
Old Farms Road.
There's an individual interested in doing a new residential construction and resubdivision
of that parcel and they've been in touch with agent Halsey.
So I would motion that we add that to the agenda under item six d.
I'll second the motion, Jed second.
>> Thank you, Jed.
Any discussion?
There are materials,
I'll display them when the topic comes up. We didn't have them in advance to to post tonight.
Assuming the motion is approved. So hearing no further discussion,
I'll call for a vote by roll call.
Vice Chair Elliott, how do you vote?
Aye.
>> Thank you. Commissioner Larson, how do you vote? Aye.
And Chairman Lally votes aye as well. The motion carries 300.
All right, the next item on the agenda is the approval of the minutes.
The 04/11/2020
special meeting minutes, which was a sidewalk
regarding application
IWWC
twenty dash twenty at 422 Lake Road.
Any discussion?
This is Jed I move we approve the minute.
This is George I second the motion.
>> Thank you. The motion is made by Commissioner Mars Larson to approve the 04/11/2020
special meeting minutes and seconded by George Elliott. Any discussion?
>> This is Jed. I would like the minutes to reflect that Jeff McGuire was at
walkthrough
that we did as well.
>> Thank you.
Any additional discussion?
Okay.
Would you like to
modify
the motion?
>> This is Jed. I'll modify I move
to modify the motion to include
Jeff McGuire as one of the attendees at the site walkthrough.
>> Thank you, Jed.
I'll second the modification of the motion.
We'll vote on the motion modification.
Vice chair Elliott, how do vote? Yes.
Chairman Larson, how do you vote?
Aye.
>> I vote aye as well. The motion to modify the motion carries three zero zero. So
the motion on the table is to approve the April 11 special meeting minutes with the addition that applicant
Jeff McGuire or property owner was present as well.
Any additional discussion?
Call for a vote to approve the minutes as modified.
Vice Chair Elliott, how do you vote? Yes.
Thank you. Chairman Larson, how do you vote? Yes.
And Chairman La la I vote I as well the motion carries 300.
The next item on the agenda is 4B, the approval of the 04/14/2020
special meeting minutes.
>> This is George Elliott. I will move to approve the minutes
of that meeting.
>> Thank you, George. And this is Jed, I second. Thank you, Jed.
The motion
made by George Elliott is to approve the 04/14/2020
special meeting minutes seconded by Jed Larson. Any discussion?
Okay, hearing none. I'll call for a vote by roll call.
Vice Chairman Elliott, how do you vote?
Yes.
>> Thank you. Chairman Larson, how do you vote? Aye.
Thank you. And this is Chairman Lally. I vote aye as well. The motion to approve the April 14 meeting minutes carries three zero zero.
All right. The next item on the agenda is item five, public comment.
Are there any and I should
so public comment is
not intended to be comment on public pending applications. You can ask for clarification
regarding details of an application such as location,
but it's not an opportunity to provide opinion on applications. This is in the public hearing.
That said,
does anyone wish to provide public comment?
Hearing none, we will move on to item 6A on the agenda,
permit application IWWC
twenty-twenty,
application by authorized agent James Blair on behalf of property owners Danielle and Jeff Maguire
for a wall rebuild and patio construction at 422 Lake Road. There were new materials submitted since the last meeting that have been posted online and distributed to the commissioners. Specifically,
there is a letter of approval from Alma for the project.
They document site photos taken by commissioner Larson
during the April 14 sitewalk visit.
Or I'm sorry. Yeah, no, they were by Jack.
Jed, I believe you're the only person
that attended that
meeting.
Is there anything you wish to share with the commission or summarize?
>> I thought both the plan to rebuild the rock wall and the patio looked
to be
positive for the homeowner, for the town, and in support of the wetlands. Everything
looked good to me.
>> Thank you, Commissioner Larson.
Agent Halsey, do you have any comments on the application?
So
I will entertain a motion if there's no additional discussion.
>> I will move to approve the application
IWWC
twenty twenty,
as described.
And this is Jed. I'll second.
>> So the motion is made by Vice Chairman Elliott to approve application IWWC
20 dash 20 seconded by Jed Larson.
Any discussion?
I have prepared the
following
special conditions based on the application
and our normal kind of special conditions for projects like this.
Number one, that the proposed regulated activities, specifically the patio
construction
shall not be installed closer than eight to 10 feet to the lake as described in the application.
The patio construction shall consist of permeable material
as described in the application and shall be maintained so as to ensure storm water infiltration during precipitation events.
Number two, soil erosion and sediment control measures shall be installed and maintained in accordance with the 2,002
Connecticut guidelines for soil erosion and sediment control.
In addition, no machinery will operate in or be placed on the lake bed. A salt fence will be placed immediately above the area of disturbance and approved by the wetlands agent prior to the commencement of any activity.
Tarps and plywood will be placed immediately in front of the wall in the lake bed and approved by the wetlands agent prior to the commencement of any activity.
At the end of each workday, any loose sediment or material shall be placed on tarp and or plywood and securely covered.
Staked
hay bales will be placed on the lakeside of the work area to prevent debris from entering the water.
Staked hay bales will be placed in any tracks or ruts that may develop. And at the conclusion of construction, these areas will be seeded and covered with straw mat to ensure revegetation.
And soil erosion
and sediment control measures shall be left in place until vegetation is well established.
Any additional discussion?
Ms. Chairman, can you email that to me?
Yes.
But I can.
Thank you.
I would also recommend that we approve the permit for a two year period.
Any additional discussion?
I will motion to modify
the original motion to include the special conditions
just read and to
define the permit duration for two years.
This is George. I will second that amendment.
Thank you. Any discussion?
>> Akin, when you made your amended motion, I thought you said two years when you did the when you were reading the conditions I thought you said three years.
No two years across the board.
Okay no other question.
>> Okay. I'll call for a vote on the amended motion.
Motion,
Vice Chairman Elliott, how do you vote? Yes.
Commissioner Larson, how do you vote? Aye.
Thank you, Chairman Lowelley. I vote aye as well. The motion is modified three zero zero.
So
call for a
vote to
approve the application with the conditions
outlined in the modified motion.
Vice chairman Elliott, how do you vote? Aye.
Thank you. Commissioner Larson, how do you vote? Aye.
Thank you. And Chairman Lally, I vote aye as well.
Motion carries three zero zero and the permit for application
I WWC
20 dash 20 is approved as noted.
The next item on the agenda,
is anyone representing that application on the call? I'm going through my list here. I see Jim.
I'm gonna unmute you, John.
There
>> will be
a letter sent out outlining everything that was just discussed with the permit. You have to wait two weeks before doing anything in case anyone wishes to appeal it.
And there will be a wetlands and water courses impact fee assessed as well. That'll be need to be paid.
Okay.
>> Any additional questions?
No, no, it's very clear. And I appreciate
everyone's
help on this. Thank you. Thank you.
Okay, the next item on the agenda is
6B, permit application
IWWC
twenty-twenty
one
by Manuel. Is Mr. Carrera on the line?
Can
we unmute Jerry?
Jerry, how do you pronounce the applicant's name? We're saying Korea.
Just like the country.
>> Oh, okay. Thank you. That's helpful. Okay. So application by is it Manuel Manuel? How does he pronounce it? He goes by Manny.
Manny Correa.
>> Perfect,
thank you. Okay, so application by Manny Correa for
a new residential construction in an upland review area at 12 Webster Lane.
I should note this application was previously characterized in our last meeting as a subdivision.
That was incorrect.
Jerry explained that this is a free cut as you would call it, so this is not a subdivision application just to be clear.
I talked with agent Halsey today.
Was a
notification of the Andover application mailed to the town of
Bolton?
>> No.
No. I did not mail them a copy of this application.
They are aware of this application because
we got a permit
from Bolton
on this project.
>> Right. Prior to submitting this application. So there's Yes.
This application
at that time. So
to be in accordance with the regulations, you need to mail a letter to them notifying them that there's an application pending in the town of
Okay. Yep. In Eiffel.
I know it's
Dotting I's And Crossing T's.
And then I think there was confusion about the fee payment. Has that been resolved?
>> Yes.
Yes. I am short
the state fee which is twice what it says on our current regulations.
>> You have to go to public hearing to update the regs but the current state fees are what is due which is $60.
Once we have those two items on the record, the application will be complete.
>> One
there's one further thing. In in our regulations, it says that
if it is a
insignificant
activity it costs
$100
and if it's a residential
activity it costs $130
and
I would suggest that this application would be
of the lower
cost
type because there's no work in the wetlands at all.
And if you if you look at the site, you'll see that there's a an existing fence that keeps everybody out of the wetlands.
>> So there's there's no filing fee for an insignificant
application. There's no no language. I
>> I I'm sure I used the term incorrectly,
but
there is a discrepancy in the or some latitude in the regulations.
>> We have a fee determination worksheet that we use to standardize
the assessment to applications. So the basic filing fee in this case would be a single family residence, which is $150
and then the additional $60 state filing fee.
Okay, so the grand total comes to $2.10?
>> And a quick look, I believe that is correct.
And then
additional fees could be
applied to the application, but for the filing fee, I think it would be $2.10. We can confirm that for you. Okay.
>> And
okay. So we can't do anything tonight because I have not submitted a letter to Bolton. Is that correct?
>> No. I think we can proceed with discussing the application
just to keep things moving. Certainly can't vote on it.
Commissioner Larson or Vice Chairman Elliott, did you want to
comment,
questions, discussion?
>> This is George Eliot. I would like to ask,
what exactly
did Bolton approve?
Since the construction that we're looking at is in Andover,
the only portion of the project
that's in Bolton
would appear to be
some kind of access,
correct?
Or
how does this work when we have
an adjoining town?
And in fact, the frontage of the property
looks like sort of a side or back lot development.
And the only portion of it, as I say, in
Bolton would be the access to the property.
So what is the town of Bolton
approving
>> when they approve the The chance oh, sorry to interrupt.
Did you have a chance to review the town of Bolton's permit
that was provided
in association with the application?
There was a copy. It should be posted online,
but it specifies that it's
the letter the permit letter reads the permitted activities within the upland review area are construction of a driveway
and grading or excavation associated with the construction noted above presumably for the Bolton portion of the property.
Okay, thank you. No, I did not see that.
>> So
yeah, they can approve.
To approve that piece of the application.
Did the commission wish to schedule a site visit?
>> This is Jed, I do
think we should schedule a site visit.
>> Well, is George. I would be amenable to a site visit.
>> Jerry, think it would be helpful to have you at the site visit.
Okay.
Unless you disagree.
No.
I'm I don't need someone to represent the application.
Yeah. No. I'm fine. I'm fine. Okay.
>> Is there a day or time that works? We typically have done Saturday mornings. I don't know if that
is an option for you.
Saturday mornings fine with me, yes.
>> Commissioner
Larson and vice chairman Elliot can you do this Saturday morning.
This
is George I'm available.
Jed's available.
Okay.
So we want our standard 09:00?
Sure. That sounds good.
I'm fine. Yep.
>> Okay.
So the commission will schedule a special meeting on this Saturday,
the date of which is
May 9 at 9AM.
Where would be the best place to meet?
>> Probably right at the site.
The address is 12 Webster Lane. There is an existing house there that is being
remodeled,
rebuilt.
So nobody's there, but there's plenty of driveway space.
And I'll let Manny know that
people will be there and we can drive right in that driveway.
>> Great.
Thank you.
Standard
social, I think we're still before the May 20 change. So standard social distancing
measures will have to apply during the site visit.
Okay, so what's
that George? They say we'll be there with masks
>> on. Yeah, I've got several.
All right. And the main purpose of the site visit would be to orient ourselves to the map that was provided with the application,
the wetlands location,
where the driver would go, where the main
residents would be.
And I'm assuming people should dress accordingly.
>> Megan, this is Jed. And I was not able to find the materials
online associated
with this
application.
I looked under the meeting for tonight,
and maybe I missed it. If you can give me a hint, I'd appreciate it. It might be under
>> last meeting's materials because it was received last meeting. Is that correct, Amanda?
>> I had my materials in that folder from last meeting, yes.
>> Yeah, and I don't think there was any additional materials submitted since last meeting.
>> Down, Jed, to last meeting's materials.
And they should be there.
>> Okay, I'll look after we get done here. I don't want to disrupt my screen and
risk whatever might happen
>> that I
did have
I reviewed the application
and for
the type of activity, I think we could use
some additional detail
regarding question nine of the application in particular, Jerry,
the erosion and sediment control measures or mitigation measures
alternatives
considered and
subsequently rejected.
If you can be prepared at the next meeting to provide greater detail on those
questions,
that would be helpful.
Okay.
>> I think it would be appropriate too to ask the applicant to notify the neighbors listed on the application of the application.
I believe agent Hallisey received at least
one inquiry from a neighbor regarding the application. So there is interest.
Okay,
we'll do.
>> And then the only other note I had was if we could be
given a written description of the construction sequence for the application.
Agent Howessey, did you have any comment on that application?
>> Just wanted to clear that it's
I have not reviewed it as far as the
division of property I understand I realized this is wetlands I just wanted to let
the record note that
vision of property has not been reviewed
and in part I bring that up because there was a lot of confusion
with the recent application
and
it wasn't differentiated between the two and
make
sure that the record
stated that
early
just wetlands
review.
>> Any additional discussion on the application,
before we move on?
Hearing none then, we will move on to item 6C on the agenda. We have a new application, application number IWWC2
for Mr.
Yanzinsky,
who I believe is on the call.
People keep moving on my screen. Oh, there you are. Okay, thank you.
Amanda, can we unmute him?
I just unmuted you. Thank you.
>> Okay. So this is an application. It should be posted online. There's several materials associated with the application
for residential demolition at 40 Townsend Road. Road.
I believe,
agent Halsey, have you been in touch with the applicant about this application?
>> Yeah we spoke for two minutes the other day,
only provided material.
Applicant did have
pre demo survey done by Mystic Air Quality which I believe a
copy of that report was provided,
and best this was abated
and I believe a clearance
clearance some
provided
but
as a note
what applicants proposing to do is is take the building down
himself.
It's really a deconstruction project
as opposed to demo. Demo is building
term.
With
there's vinyl siding on the property now,
he intends to take that off. Underneath it there is no
flat board.
Now the house was built in the eighteen hundreds I believe and
most definitely
would would have been wood sided at that time. Apparently was removed
so any lead there wouldn't be any lead paint.
There's typically
with a demo project
very often they're wetted
Building
wet in order to minimize dust.
Could be an issue. In
this case it's not.
In the fact that there
is no there's no wood
hiding.
Believe he intends to
reuse a lot of material.
Part of the reason I think he's taking it apart for what he is.
But I did want to bring up a question.
Are
we planning to rebuild on the same
foundation?
No.
>> The reason I ask is could trigger some zoning issues. I will I will bring those up now and then. No, I'm not planning to rebuild on the same foundation.
>> Thank you. The application stated that you were going to be refilling in the basement and to current grade?
>> Yes,
there's a small basement. It's not underneath the entire house, but
I obviously need to fill it in. I'm not gonna leave a hole just sitting around.
>> If
the commission recalls, we did previously do a sidewalk at this location. There was a previous application that was subsequently withdrawn.
Does the commission wish to do another sidewalk?
I don't
feel it necessary
or useful.
Thank you. I agree with you.
>> Okay. I agree as well assuming none of the locational features of the property have changed which I don't believe they have. Don't think another sidewalk is necessary.
We
>> will cross that off our list.
So we
cannot,
we'll receive the application tonight. We need to wait at least two weeks before making any decisions on it.
So we can
discuss the application further at our June meeting if there's no additional
questions for the applicant.
I have no other questions.
This is George. I have no questions.
>> Okay.
Agent Halsey,
could you draft
erosion and sediment control? Can you work with the applicant to outline an erosion and sediment control plan
should the application be approved?
Certainly.
You. You
want that for the next meeting?
Yes, please.
Thank you.
>> Yeah, I believe the letter provided indicated that
there wasn't
specific measures outlined but that the applicant was willing to implement whatever measures were recommended by the commission.
Correct
all right so we will
move on then
>> one
comment please
I'm not able to immediately locate this application on the town website,
and it was not included in the email
attachments
for this meeting.
So I would appreciate
if we could
ensure that we get a copy of this application.
>> So I believe Amanda has it currently displayed from the town website. Amanda, are you able to go back to Yes, John. Can everyone see my screen?
>> I can see the application on screen. It's showing page 107,
yes.
>> Okay, yep. This is on the website.
So I will show you all the information for this application.
So everything for 40 Townsend Road is listed here.
>> Can you scroll up, Amanda, just to kinda show what page you're on? Yeah, so if you go
>> to boards and committees.
Yeah, that's where I started. Go to appointed and then click on Inland Wetlands.
>> So you have to scroll down.
And scroll down and scroll down and scroll The current moving documents.
Wait a minute, I lost it.
>> I'm working on my other screen. Trust me, it'll look so much better with our new website soon. I promise. I think we'll access to the improved,
yes.
Coming soon, but for now it's all listed here.
>> Oh, okay, current meeting document. I shouldn't scroll down for now. Thank you. Got it.
Okay, welcome.
Merci.
I'm
>> having trouble with
the town email sharing documents, so I apologize.
I
will work to get them to Amanda and then
send links to you guys, I think might be the best way to approach it because the email system seems to be removing attachments that I try to send out. That's been challenging for us. But everything I've received
prior to today
related to applications
is up on the website.
>> So please let me know if you'd like to see any of these documents right now.
Nope.
Got that one.
>> So let's move on.
Mr. Yanzitski, before we move on actually, do you have any questions
of the commission? Yes.
>> So I don't want my application to be
rolled
in
incomplete.
I have not
submitted payment for it yet or the fees.
Yes.
Could you tell me how much and is it just a check that I write to town of Andover and send it in or? Yeah, thank you. Your email actually prompted us to
>> include a note on this webpage
to help clarify that for applicants.
So yes, if you can make a check out to the town of Andover
and we will confirm with you but I think it would be
the $60 state fee along with
for a single family residence $150
so $210
to the town of Andover and then you can mail it to town hall.
Okay,
>> thank you. You're welcome. And we're trying to provide applicants with a little bit of leniency with the payment since you obviously can't walk into town hall and pay right now.
We have it by next meeting. I think you should be okay.
>> All right very good so next meeting is next month first month yes
>> I believe June 1 I don't have a calendar in front of me
pull my calendar up for you Well, that's easy enough.
Okay. Just wanted to make sure we hadn't
done a special date. Let me double check.
Nope. It is still June 1.
Thank you. You're very welcome.
All right, so we'll move on to new item 6D,
which is the pre application request
for 26 Old Farms Road.
These materials I will have to pull up on my screen because I did not have a chance to ask Amanda to post them. Amanda, how do I take over screen share?
Hey, Megan?
Okay.
You can try now.
>> Hi. This is this is Eric Lateska. I'll
be probably speaking to this pre application thing. I I actually have, another drawing that might be, a little bit better for for us to look at. I could share my screen if that would help.
Can you do that Amanda?
>> So Eric, if you see at the bottom of your screen,
the green button, feel free to share screen.
Eric, how do you pronounce your last name?
Oh good question, Loteska.
Loteska, thank you. Okay
we can see it.
Yeah.
Okay,
everyone can see it?
>> Eric can you just tell us your interest in the property?
>> Yeah,
so pre application is definitely accurate here. This is,
we have no interest in the property other than
perhaps a future interest.
It's on the market for sale. We
got to the point where we were negotiating with the sellers before the health crisis
really took root and then it's kind of stalled.
But we're still sort of hoping to understand
a couple of things about what we may or may not be able to do with the property,
that brought us first to the, Planning and Zoning Commission a couple of weeks ago, and now we're here with
a new set of questions for the for the Wetlands Commission.
Okay. Thank you.
>> I should say there's two of us here
on the call. My brother-in-law George Correa,
he and I, I guess, are both representing our households because
what we have sought out to do,
know, if not with 26 Old Farms Road, perhaps some other land, is to sort of, join forces,
in acquiring some land, maybe splitting
it in half, subdividing it, and then potentially building two separate single family dwellings on the land.
We came
across 26 Old Farms Road,
and the acreage, you know, was in the neighborhood we were looking for,
and
we're
basically in the process of trying to figure out whether or not we could essentially subdivide the property
into two lots.
And
the issue that brings us before this commission is basically getting access
to the land.
The land is actually here outlined
in red. I'm kind of going over it with
my mouse pointer to show you what it is. This is
on this drawing, lot 3.
If you get rid of all the colors, this drawing was actually submitted
with a building
permit application
where this orange area was, was the original
plan for the buildable area. The current owners had this drawn up
and submitted.
We
grabbed the records from the town and started drawing on top of it to
show some concepts.
Maybe most importantly for this group,
what's outlined in red or
rather green here is the wetlands
as they were drawn
back in the early 2000s.
So we recognize that there's some, you know, some time has gone by, but that's what we're working with
for Quick the
>> question, sorry to interrupt you. So House Number 1, was that built as drawn?
>> No, a little bit of
excavation
was done and
some work on a
driveway
accessing
the land was
done. A little bit of clearing and I think some materials were brought in, but
no building, there was no foundation or anything poured.
It stopped
and
the property's been on the market for some time.
>> Your background,
do you have expertise? Are you a developer
in construction?
>> No. So,
actually, I, you know, I kinda when I was going through what I wanted to say here, I wanted to actually start off by introducing myself and and my brother-in-law really quickly. You know, there's two families involved. I just wanna, you know, for this commission,
know, not not a matter of real,
official business here, but, like, you know, we're two we're two close families. We're looking to move into town.
My wife is actually a teacher at the elementary school. She's been there for almost fifteen years. My daughter's enrolled in the pre
K program.
Both George and his wife and then our family, we're looking to set ourselves up in the next community
for the next phase of our lives here.
We're not looking to develop and
sell this property.
My
background is actually, I'm
in insurance, but
George, my brother-in-law is,
and George, you know, keep me honest here, feel free to speak up, but George is a superintendent at
a at a general contractor.
He's got experience kind of overseeing a range of
construction projects, working with the the
officials in the building department, zoning department, things like that.
And George, you know, George really kinda is the brains of the operation. If any difficult questions get asked, I promise you,
I'm gonna throw it over to him pretty quickly.
>> And that's what I was trying to assess, was whether you're happy, if we had technical questions, whether your background allowed you to, you know, be able to answer them or not.
Does the commission have any questions at this point?
>> This is George Elliott.
And I wondered if,
since there was clearly
a lot designated
and
you mentioned some
activities
that would have been
probably under
the
jurisdiction of the Inland Wetlands Commission at that time.
Are you aware of any permit
having been issued
for that activity?
>> Yes,
there was. There was
an erosion and sediment control plan that was submitted and approved
and that was the work that they started.
So what they started to do was
they set up
a
runoff pond,
they set up
silt fencing,
and they began some work on the road or the drive going to the
house buildable area that's highlighted in orange.
And then
that work started, but for whatever reason, it stopped and then the
land went on to the market.
Okay. Thank you.
>> So
just so I I actually have another view that's a little more zoomed in, I think, on the important area that that, you know, we'd like to talk about specifically, but just to orientate you a little bit.
This is a, this lot, Lot Number 3, is a rear lot.
Old Farms Road is up here. It's actually
not in the picture. You follow this up, this is a driveway.
It's actually an easement with a driveway on it. There's a two way easement between
the current owners of this property of the land, Lot 3,
and this
lot just beside here.
Therein kind of lies
a potential problem for us. Guess
the reason we're before the committee here is because
we know having spoken with the zoning,
planning and zoning committee is that you know basically there's two, there's three things that,
need to happen in order for us to be able to access this land and to be able to get to two
subdivided
parcels.
Right now the way the easement works is, you know, this this land would have access through the easement.
The,
in order to get to the second
buildable area back here that we've just sort of conceptually drawn up at the moment,
you know, a driveway could be,
or a drive of some kind could have been, can be cleared
giving access through,
through the front part of the lot, I guess the front basically the way the drawing is showing here.
Is the obstacles there
are one, of course, getting the party that uses the driveway already to agree to the easement to make it three way. We're,
we're unsure of the what the outcome to that
to that could be.
The another issue is, of course,
the elevation on this map isn't really shown, but at least the way that this is drawn, we know that there's
a pretty steep grade through here.
Know, we'd
either have to we think it's outside of the regulation. The zoning regulation
may force us to either do some grading at least, if not do some paving,
could drive the cost of the project up pretty considerably.
And then, of course, the three way driveway actually requires a variance from the zoning regulations.
I
don't know, you know, I don't get the sense that the outlook on that is, you know, is that it's impossible. So I think it's the uncertainty really comes from the other
household that uses the driveway and then, you know, some of the issues with crossing the land.
So,
you know, we're before this committee to actually ask about this,
potential leg,
from another street,
Pine Ridge Drive.
This is actually land,
that belongs to this, to this lot. This little strip of land goes up.
George, I if I'm let me know if I'm wrong here. I think across the way,
directly across
perpendicular to the two lines, it's fifty fifty feet across.
50 feet. Okay.
>> And the radius up here says 75 feet.
We know we can meet the zoning
requirements
in terms of
the width of the driveway.
The issue is, of course, that we run, you know, this would be going over
this wetland area where runoff
from
Old Farms Road
runs,
and and goes through, you know, right through here.
Have you walked the property?
>> Yeah a few maybe a dozen times or so we've we've walked we've walked this quite a bit. We actually just visited over the weekend to take some field measurements of this.
>> Okay can you understand that you're not a soil scientist or a wetland scientist,
do you feel that that's an accurate depiction that there's wetlands in that area
near Pine Ridge?
>> Yeah, I mean it
looks you know very similar
to what we see when we get down there. I will say we, you know,
there's a low lying area,
that
seems to be maybe a little bit,
bigger than this.
When we scale this and take measurements, I think this area we came up with,
George, 1,500
square feet or?
>> Yeah, in scaling the drawing
from what was delineated as wetlands from this original sketch here,
it comes out to about 1,500 square feet.
But we went out and just field measured,
you know, with a tape measure
and we were closer to 2,500 square feet. Well, we believe 2,500
square feet. So it seemed a little bit bigger
in field condition.
>> So this may be this may be accurate as as actual wetland. I think our measurement was really of, a low lying area
that that extended perhaps a little bit wider than this,
but I you know, we're we're thinking about the area that we we, you know, would need some fill and some construction and you know obviously the
work to make sure that water flow isn't disturbed
under any circumstances.
I think the area
we're talking about is more like 2,500 square feet.
>> It's curious to me that there's that kind of kick out to Pine Ridge. Does the current property owner have any
insight on that? I mean, to me, almost would suggest that the intention was to develop it in that direction, but
just curious if you know the history of the property and why there is that little piece to Pine Ridge.
>> We haven't been told any
history of why that
access was given to Pine Ridge like that.
>> But it's on the original subdivision plan, right George? Yes.
So when does that date back to?
Late 80s,
'88,
'89, I believe.
Right, The Woodlands?
Yeah, it's The Woodlands 2.
Yeah.
So
how
can I help you?
>> Okay, so thank you for, you know, first letting me go through all that.
What we're trying to understand, one is like, we form some kind of an outlook of the way of what this commission would say?
Would you be approving of something like this or there maybe
if that's too much to ask,
you know, without without an application is, you know, like, what's
what are the the regulations
that may permit or prohibit us from doing something like this so that, you know, we can get our bearings and and form our,
form our own outlook.
Because as I said,
this is property that's on the market that we are,
you know, perhaps looking to acquire, but I think, you know, understanding whether or not we're gonna be able to do some of the things that we we are trying to do here
ultimately is going to probably determine whether or not we're
making offers.
>> Sure. So
wetlands,
we
try to be aware of zoning concerns and that's why we have a commissioner that is appointed to sit on both commissions.
But we don't make our decisions based on any of the zoning requirements.
Our
job is to look at an application based on the impact to wetlands or watercourses
regardless of who else might look at it and approve it.
But we're a small town, we try to you know, save people headache when possible and point out, you know, possible conflicts that might come up.
And we've been fortunate in the past to have someone who served both as zoning agent and wetland agent. And and Jim's currently,
assuming that role in the interim as well, to try and help bridge that gap. So the zoning issues that you've brought up, I don't think we can help you with, in terms of wetland because it's it's outside of our purview.
In terms of wetlands, I mean, we might be able we have in the past when someone came before us asking to subdivide a property, we talked to them about things,
ways to be
more environmentally sensitive with the design approach
and gave them some suggestions to consider before submitting an application.
I don't think it would be unreasonable
for the commission to do that.
Jed or George, I don't know if you want to weigh in with any thoughts.
>> Well, this is George Elliott. And it seems to me that,
fundamentally, from our point of view, from the inland wetlands point of view, what you'd be looking for would be a permit for wetland crossing.
Yes. Exactly.
>> And that's pretty straightforward.
And
as
Chairman Lawley says,
we have
discussed
such
pre applications
previously,
and it wouldn't be
beyond
the scope of our effort
to look at a preliminary
plan
for such a
crossing
prior to an actual
application.
So if we were But the point would be, you would be leading toward
application
for a
wetland crossing.
And that's what we'd be willing
to
>> review and comment on. Well, just a point of clarification.
If any of the activity is within 100 feet of a wetlands,
you would need a wetlands permit.
So just it's not just the problem if you end up, taking the other approach,
you still may need a wetlands permit for this application without knowing distances offhand I can't say yes or no for sure.
And in order to
give you a permit either way, we would need a wetlands delineation probably in this case. So I think we
would be inclined to
request a new wetlands delineation for sure.
Do you have a sense between the two driveway options?
Is one longer than the other, I guess is the simplest way to put it?
>> Yes,
so if we were to come in and access the
back house from
Pine Ridge that driveway would be
approximately
feet or so. If
we were to access that same
rear house from
Old Farms.
Not including what's
part of what the two way split driveway,
it would be about 1,600 feet.
And it would actually be closer to 2,000
feet or so, 2,100 feet from the house driveway
to Old Farms.
So that's
another thing that it's a very, very long driveway.
So
>> with that thought in mind,
are you considering having both properties
access
from Pine Ridge Drive or is the only scenario from Pine Ridge House 2?
>> House 2 would be from Pine Ridge and House 1 would be from Old Farms. Okay. That's
what we're thinking.
Okay. Is that preferred
application?
Yes.
Okay.
>> It also yeah. Sorry. Okay. With that in mind, because I think it's easier to discuss one scenario than multiple scenarios.
Yes.
>> So
let's
talk is that we submit an application to wetlands,
all other factors resolved by everybody else. House one would come in from Old Farms and house two would come in from Pine Ridge Drive.
So
that middle middle section of the driveway between House 1 And 2 would be eliminated.
Correct.
>> Also, we've been talking with a civil engineer.
It's Bushnell Associates.
They were the outfit that originally
did the
surveying
and they
did the delineation of the wetlands and they did the deep hole percolation test for House 1.
And he's very familiar with the area in this particular piece of property because I guess they've done quite a bit of work there.
But he thought in his mind that they could fairly easily
make a crossing there
with minimal
impact to the wetlands and
virtually no impact to the water flow that goes through there. We would do like a culvert or whatever is required. We would get a hydrolysis to come and
make a design for us and you know we would do everything
with
the least amount of impact
and footprint to that area.
>> So
I intentionally didn't mention this previously because I didn't wanna sway the conversation in any direction. I live on Pine Ridge Drive on the other side of the street from where the driver would be coming in.
Oh, okay. So I don't think I would not benefit any more or less than anyone else in the universe from your proposal. So I don't think
that matters. Other than that, I'm very familiar with, at least the manager side of the property.
There
was a case in town previously where someone was requesting an easement in that case through town property
to do kind of an
unusual construction.
In that case, they had to span a brook.
I thought in the materials that I had seen there was mention of a stream in this property. Is it just a wetlands or is there an actual watercourse?
>> It's seasonal.
And
when it rains, there is some water flow, but for the rest of the time, it seems that it's just,
you know, like
damp in, you know, in sort of muddy.
Okay. But we went when we went there on Saturday there was water flowing there it was about maybe two inches of water
flowing.
>> The lots are really small on Pine Ridge so
one concern I would raise would be you know making absolute certain that whatever
crossing was designed,
there would be no concern of backflow or flooding of the adjacent property.
>> Yes,
and that we would rely on a civil engineer in hydrolysis
to
calculate
that and to make sure that that wouldn't happen.
So I would basically over design it.
>> Yes.
And we have no problem me knowing in
going
size larger what pipe or whatever may, you know, whatever is required to make sure that
that we wouldn't be any future issues.
Vice Chairman Elliott, did you want to say something?
>> Okay, I wondered if
speaking of future impact,
this water court you mentioned
is
essentially
from
Times Road
and more or less downslope
towards Pine Ridge Drive,
am I correct?
>> It seems the water that's accumulated in
this area
from, it comes from two catch basins
that are on Old Farms Road.
And they discharge
into
an area alongside of 20
Old Farms Road.
And then from there.
That's where the.
Eric, if you come up closer to the number 17.
But know the other way.
Yeah.
The to catch basins discharge into an area over here,
or the water then
makes its way down the hill.
And
there's also runoff because there's
a lot of slope in here
where the
two property lines are from Lot 2 to Lot 1.
So all of the water that's running
off the surface
basically ends up down into that little valley where we wanna make our crossing.
Okay.
>> And then the water continues on
looking at the map to the left.
And then
I haven't walked down that way to see where it actually goes but it just continues on to the left
That valley there, there's a it's about a
it's about a 30 foot drop
from
out here
to here
maybe.
>> Oh, from there to the other side where the 75 foot
back lot line is or so. Yeah.
Yeah.
>> That's there's a it's about 100 foot crossing
and it drops down about 30 feet.
>> Commissioner Larson, is there anything you wanted to?
Any thoughts you can provide given you're sitting on planning and zoning as well and might have some sense of how it would be received there?
>> Well, I don't know if
Jim had spoken to the applicant since the last
discussion of planning and zoning, but we did have Jim and I when we talked about this a little bit following, we were concerned about the ability
to provide frontage
on both of the lots.
And when we discussed it at planning and zoning, we thought the width of that little strip going out to Pine Ridge Road was 75 feet wide.
And so you could have a rear lot using the open space subdivision with a minimum frontage of 35 feet, so you could split that.
Now that it's only 50 feet, if you were to split it between the two lots to provide any frontage at all,
you don't have the 35
feet per lot, which is the requirement for open space subdivision.
I think the 50 foot that you have there is because that's the minimum for a rear lot under normal subdivision rules.
So I know Jim had a concern about,
you know, having a lot with no frontage
being problematic?
And I bring that up in the wetlands meeting because I know time is of the essence for you guys. Yeah,
>> I thought it was it was my
understanding that for a
ARD open space rear lot
with deed restrictions.
It was a 50 foot.
I'm sorry, it was 25 feet per lot,
which that puts us at 50 feet and that's what we have there.
>> I'd have to go back and look, I can't remember and I don't have those regulations in front of me right now. Just I did
my thinking based on 75 feet across there and thought that that would not be a problem for you. Now,
I don't know and I'll have to go take a look at that. If you say you've looked at it and it's 25 feet, that could still work then.
>> Is the frontage, I mean, I know this is a zoning thing,
but is the frontage here based on this radius or is it based strictly on this diameter? I mean, there's 75 feet of frontage to the street with a radius in it.
>> Well, and that's a fine point. The regulations talk about the width of the strip going to the rear lot, and that would be 50 feet as opposed to 75.
Okay.
>> I'm sorry, Jeff. So I would ask Jim if you've got any insight, you know, based on you're looking at that over the last couple of weeks.
>> My recollection was.
Looking at the screen
at the planning and zoning meeting.
I was caught off guard because one of the lots didn't have any frontage
at all
and I've spent some time with George looking at this
and I don't recall ever that came up.
I believe it's 25 feet
25 foot for the rear lot.
Now that you bring it up, I'm not quite sure how it's measured, and
I know how a lot width is measured, but but I'm not sure how the the rear lot
for the ARD is measured, whether there's.
>> Jim, I just went to our chart and and he is correct. It is 25 feet required frontage for the open space subdivision.
>> Frontage or lot width? I mean, we use the term lot width.
Lot width shouldn't be an issue
And I don't know why it was 50
you know why
it would have been 50
feet.
It is
minimum for a a road
roadway.
Might have been
consideration at that time.
It seems to work for
an ARD subdivision.
NARD,
yeah, the open space.
Relax.
>> Agent Halsey,
since
if they were to purchase the property, they would probably be leaning on you to help prepare both applications for zoning and for wetlands.
Do you have any questions of the commission that we could answer right now for you?
>> Oh, I wanted to get a sense
as
how the commission might view. I I view this as an intermittent stream.
And it I did I walked
in from Pine Ridge Drive, not coming off of old farms.
And it drops
fairly abruptly
as you as you approach that intermittent stream
and
that would be
fair amount of fill you brought in.
>> So it drops down towards the stream and then climbs back up the hill to where the residents would be? Yes.
>> Okay. I didn't actually experience that climb just because I I stopped there.
Okay.
But obviously, that's
>> So understanding you're not an engineer,
would it be feasible
to put a structure across to span it?
>> Is that question for Jim or is that for us? Sorry. Anyone that feels like an answer. Yes.
Could be yes.
Okay, so it's not impossible.
>> No, no.
Okay.
My concern was was I know the commission looked at alternatives.
Yes.
And
she's trying to identify
deal breaker early on.
>> That's what the applicant obviously wants to do. Sure, likewise. I think as we walk through this application, it seems like maybe
I don't know how the easement access came to be from the initial attempt at developing it, but it seems like it actually may have been intended to be developed from the Pine Ridge Drive side.
Yeah, that could be true.
>> I'm not sure we can offer you much more than what we've given you tonight at this point.
I don't know if this has been helpful for you guys or
>> It has been.
Can I just pick a little bit of that last topic about whether
or not
trucking in some fill and having a culvert? I mean, think that's the distinction that's being made there. And I don't know if the intermittent stream versus just wetland
has some bearing on the difference here with how we cross that area,
but,
I mean, if
we weren't trying to build up the area, you know, to sort of match the elevation on both sides with fill,
it would still dip down.
Is that something
that could work or are
we really talking about having to have something span these two elevated areas?
>> I'm not sure about seeing the site or at least photos of it to really better understand the topography and hydrology there that we could answer that question.
I think it's likely that commission would want you to be as environmentally
conservative as possible with the application design.
>> Would it make sense for us to
have
civil
engineer
come up with
an initial
plan
and submit it to you guys for some review?
>> I mean, that's up to you whether you want to outlay that expense. It's sort of a fuzzy zone. Don't know.
I don't know if we've ever, know, like looked at a plan for a property that was owned by somebody else for the you know, the two parties in discussion were not, one of the owners.
So
>> it start I mean, I think at some point,
you guys will have to take
a leap and you know,
risk potentially being turned down at, other wetlands or zoning.
I don't think from at least a wetlands perspective,
I think there's certainly ways that
unless there's something
that hasn't come up like a, I don't know, I can't even think of an example. But based on what you presented to us tonight,
I think there's certainly solutions
that could be made because our job is not to prevent development.
It's just to make sure that if it's done, it's done in the best possible way to protect.
I do think there's solutions for that.
>> The zoning issue, can't help you with. If I could just address Eric's question perhaps,
mean a culvert would still involve a significant amount of fill,
not that you would be spanning
that
wetlands.
You'd have both a covered and fill, significant fill.
>> Yep.
I just, yeah, mean I just,
I don't want to
make it seem like there's a 30 foot drop in elevation
we are going to span over 100 feet with fill.
Is not, you know,
whatever got designed,
given
that it is going to manage the water flow properly,
I don't think we would fill any higher than we actually need to to make sure that
the flow of the water isn't disrupted.
Is that right, George? Am I describing that?
>> Yes, we would fill it in so that we would meet the minimum
slope grading regulations that are by the town, which are
basically
anything less than 10% can be a
gravel driveway, and anything between 10 to 15%
can has to be paved,
and nothing greater than 15% so we would be somewhere.
Preferably in the
nine
to 10%
grade
and keep it gravel.
So we would probably have to lift it up probably about,
I'm guessing
about 15 feet
in order to make those numbers work.
So we're looking at probably bringing in
somewhere around a thousand yards of materials.
>> I mean, my guess is
kind of knowing the site a little bit,
it may be intermittent and not have a lot of flow, when it does not flow, I would expect a lot of flow coming off of that and fast.
Yeah, for develops it, it would be in their interest to make sure that the design can handle that so it doesn't wash out especially if it's your only.
>> Yeah, and speaking with Andrew, who's the civil engineer that I was talking with, they would do it.
I think the way he worded it was to the one hundred year flood or something along those lines.
He thought they would probably be
like a 30 to 36 inches pipe that goes across there, which is that's a big pipe.
>> Yeah,
and so my, my background is natural resources.
Do river and stream monitoring and stuff like that. So I have some,
some knowledge of this stuff. I'm not an engineer, however.
But just kind of knowing knowing the property a little bit, you know, not that particular location, but I would expect it to be a really, a really flashy system.
So if it's, you know, draining that development up top.
>> Yeah, and he thought that it might even be multiple pipes too.
>> That's what yeah, I think if
part of that fill is, know, culverts that are allowing water through them.
I think there are options available too.
>> Megan, this is Jed. Is this something
that we ought to take a sidewalk on
before the next meeting or does that get the cart on the wrong side of the horse?
>> I think all things considered between the fact that it's not an application,
coronavirus
and everything else in between, I'm kind of inclined to say no on that unless others feel strongly in a different direction.
Megan, this is Linda. Yes. The
people presenting don't even own the property anyway, so
True.
>> That was the point I wanted to make. This is George. And I think that given the fact that,
again, the discussion
is purely theoretical at this point, I don't think we should
make any time
to visit
the location.
>> Okay.
So it sounds like
the commission does not wish to schedule a site visit at this point.
You can continue
to work with agent Halsey to try to put together an application if you'd like to submit one before the commission obviously to
either purchase the property or finance arrangement with the current owner to be able to do that.
But I think that would be the next step that we'd be able to entertain.
Okay, thank
>> you for your time. I appreciate it. Thank you. Yes, thank you. And sorry, sorry we ended up on the topic of zoning and
planning, but we appreciate everyone's
patience and thank you for all the information.
>> No problem. Thank you both.
All right, so let's move on the agenda
item
seven a,
enforcement actions.
Agent Halsey, do you have any updates to report on the violation
reported at Townsend Road?
>> Spoke to Beth Hagerty
today.
He indicated he's still recuperating from surgery. He indicated he would take care of the brush
sometime in June.
>> Is that satisfactory from your perspective? Yes.
Commissioner Larson or Vice Chairman Elliott,
do you wish to comment?
>> This is George Elliott. I haven't seen any activity there. Again, as Jim says,
conclusion. We wouldn't expect to see anything going on there. And I don't see any
reason to
pursue it any further at this point. I think that Jim is correct. The matter is in hand.
Thanks, Jed. I agree with George.
Okay.
>> All right. So we'll just ask, I guess, even how we'll see maybe revisit in June prior to our meeting and see if there's anything that warrants
the
commission to review.
Okay. So we'll move on to item seven b.
Notice of violation regarding a disturbance to a wetland at 28 Shotty Mill Road.
>> Yeah I did.
I got a call
on that I had gone out there, I got a call before I actually issued notice,
right, and
I went out and I spoke to the owner and I followed up
with a letter
letting him know that he needs
secure a permit for
any activity within 100 feet or at least go to wetlands
he's doing any any work within 100 foot of and
he was amenable to that.
Basically I asked him to
give me a call and go over the particulars.
He had no real project going on.
Owns some heavy equipment and he and he seems to be doing Genenza but
I'll work with him.
>> Okay. Thank you. Commissioner
Larson or Vice Chairman Elliott, any comment?
George Elliott, no comments.
Chad, no comments.
>> We'll move on then to item seven c,
an order to remediate and we may wanna just combine discussion for seven c and seven d.
There was an order to remediate issued for properties
41 Route 87 and 33 Route 87
owned by Sandra Nichols and Kurt Bohm respectively.
Agent Halsey can you provide updates on the status of that enforcement action?
>> Okay I speak to Sandra Nichols owner of 41
Route 87.
I had a little trouble getting a hold of her. She's working with an attorney. She wants some further information
on contractor and she wants some oversight,
and I am working on that.
I also
spoke to Bert
Boehm owner of the
property at 33 and
he
we discussed
whether he definitively had to move the shed off the property or whether the Commission would entertain
an alternative.
We're looking at that
as a possibility.
Unfortunately, it's a pretty tight, very tight lot. There's not a lot of property. There's not a lot of space on that property
that is
100 feet from wetlands.
Looking at the possibility of
presenting
he's looking at the possibility of presenting an alternative application
would allow for
placing the shed on the surface he is able to
to do, he is not required to to put frost protection in per building code if it's a shed under 600
square feet.
So that's an option that he'd like to explore.
Hopefully I will have.
A little better direction on the actual.
Removal of.
Material.
In the near future,
few weeks.
Chairman Elliot or Commissioner Larson, any questions or comments?
George Elliott, no questions or comments.
Jed, no questions.
>> Okay, thank you.
We will move on then to item 7E under enforcement.
A cease and desist order was issued
regarding removal and deposition of material into a wetland without a permit. We held a special meeting on the fourteenth.
That was a show cause hearing associated with that.
And
agent Halsey, can you provide us with an update on that enforcement action?
>> I did get a call from the owner, Ruby, as
she
was encouraged to contact
me at the last meeting.
And she actually provided me with with
a map of wetland soils.
Apparently she had one from
had one prepared when they did an addition on the property a couple years ago.
So it's a start and I did speak to
actually her husband, Ruby's husband, over the weekend and he's preparing them.
He's having his architect prepare a plan it's rather an ornate fence
and
I've gotten a lot of calls, a lot of interest in this, a lot of concern.
Hopefully I will have a plan
>> I did just ask to pull up the wetlands
map that was submitted
just so I see.
>> It should be relatively easy to transfer that information on the wetlands
map that she had done
onto a base map.
Seems like it would be workable.
>> Is this it Megan? Yes thank you. So as I understood it in reading through the report basically the area
within the bounds labeled number three
was delineated as wetland soil.
>> I don't think this was the map that she provided but I could be wrong. It
was
colored colored map.
It was on
>> I might not have received that map because I think this was the report that I was given.
>> Okay. What I've seen, and it seems to be just a generalized
soils map
with,
you know, Woodridge,
Charlton's,
Paxton's, you know, various soil types,
but I don't see this as delineating
wetlands.
Okay. She did Yeah, provide me
>> let me check my files real quick and see if it didn't.
I think the only thing I received was this report.
Yeah. I think what I what was posted was all I received. So if you have any additional Zoom that you can share, can you send it to us? I will send it.
George, to your comment,
the report does indicate that it was based on a field inspection
where they
Yeah.
>> But this attachment
is simply of SOLS. I realized that a SOLS survey was done and a wetland survey was done referred to in the letter, but the attachment
is simply an NRCS SOLS map.
So
>> we're looking for a map that might include the pink flagging tape sequence stuff one through 12?
Okay.
Alright. If you have something additional, Jim, can you share it with the commission?
Yeah. Right now, I will send I it don't mean right now. Prior to the next meeting. I will. Yes. Okay. Thank you.
Okay, so I think that concludes enforcement.
Was there any further discussion or comments on item 7E?
Commissioner Larson or Vice Chairman Elliott?
I'm
sorry.
I had no comment.
>> Okay.
So hearing none, we'll move on to item eight public comment.
Any public comment at this time?
Amanda, is there a way to unmute all? Don't know how are people able to unmute themselves?
>> One
by one
and
see who would like to participate.
>> Obviously, how
do people tell us if they wish to comment?
So first we'll start off with Janus.
Hi, no comment.
>> Okay.
Scott, Persson, did you want to participate at all?
I'm all set, Amanda.
Okay.
Jeff Maguire,
would you like to speak?
>> You're not good there.
Hank, would you like to participate?
No, I'm all set. Thanks Amanda.
>> Okay.
Amanda, quick Thanks for
Quick question for the board. Can everybody hear me? Yes.
So I have asked a couple of times to get the town's potential project
on the corner of Shawty And Wales
looked at.
Do we have
any further discussion on that from the Wetlands Commission?
I did speak with Jim about that earlier today and we decided not to add it to the agenda because we didn't have
anything to look at.
So I think if you can get us a
a map or a photo or, you know, just anything that the commission could actually look at in order to discuss, that would be helpful.
Okay.
>> We did also talk about,
you know, if there's
no,
there's no language for emergency repairs in wetlands.
But if it if it needs to be done, it can be done. And I know that the violation can be issued just to follow, you know, procedure and an application submitted
after that.
Understood.
>> So if you would like to submit an application at the June meeting, we can receive one then if you need us to do something sooner, we could call a special meeting if needed.
Okay.
>> Okay. I think that covered everyone for public comment. Under other business item nine,
I had put wetlands enforcement officer and duly authorized agent discussion.
For the latter part, I had put that on last meeting's agenda, but if I recused myself from voting, we didn't have a quorum, so we just decided to push it to this agenda. But I did complete
the state's wetland training.
So if the commission wanted to, it could authorize me
to serve as a duly authorized agent to
review
and approve permits in the upland review area
that have
only suspected to be minimal or no impact. And then
other towns have put further restrictions on their duly authorized agents where
if it's a commercial application, it automatically has to go to the commission. If it's greater than a certain acreage,
it automatically has to go to the commission. I'm trying to think what other examples were put out there or just restricting it to things like
sheds and decks and stuff like that. So
I'm not advocating for it, not necessarily looking for more work, but I understand that it's been a challenge for Jim to fill in as in the wetlands role and that there's some things that maybe don't really need a thorough review by wetlands.
So I will put that out there for the commission if they want to consider it. And on the wetlands officer
side of things,
just again thanking Jim for stepping up and agreeing to serve as wetlands agent.
It was an interim agreement though, so
I would like to remind
the
town management that we need a wetlands agent. We need one badly.
And I would hope that we can come up with a solution before our June meeting.
>> Megan, this is George Elliott.
I
would be happy to see you duly authorized,
and I just sure hope we'll have a quorum
at a
meeting soon,
in order to be able to
take that issue,
to vote.
>> Megan or Amanda, do you know if we have any applicants for the position yet?
>> Hi Jed, unfortunately
we have not.
I talked I spoke with Megan last week, and I know that it's a
it's an issue, and it's
one of my projects for this week to
spread the word even more that
we are looking for someone
to fill the role.
And I just wanted to thank Megan for all the efforts that she's put in. I know it's been a long time.
And Jim.
Oh, yeah. And Jim has really stepped up and we really appreciate it.
And
let's all put it out there, I would say,
to any contacts we have. I know Megan sent us a few.
So if you have any leads,
feel free to send them our way.
But it's definitely a priority.
>> I had previously
looked into we are technically in the Eastern Connecticut Conservation District, but we
sit right on the boundary of I believe it's the Central Connecticut Conservation District. So
I think when Josh Narski first resigned, I reached out to the ECCD,
the Eastern District,
to explore using them as a wetlands agent.
At the time we decided it was cost prohibitive.
We have to pay an annual membership fee and then that would bring the hourly rate down to about $56 an hour, which was significantly higher than we had anticipated hiring at.
However, we've had no success so far in recruiting an individual.
So I've also reached out to the Central Conservation District more recently, they just hired an individual from Coventry to serve as one of their staff people and that individual will be serving as Coventry's wetland agent.
She's new, so she'll be green and in need of training. But I wondered if it didn't make sense
to have her also serve as
and over agent and maybe get a
reduced rate given that she doesn't have experience
even just to do some of the administrative stuff that
Susan's not able to do and Jim really may not have the time to do.
So I wanted the town to consider at least in the interim
potentially taking on one of the conservation districts understanding that
because the price is substantially higher than what we were hoping to pay someone hourly,
the number of hours available would be reduced.
But quite frankly, I can't keep doing the level of work I've been doing
to support the commission.
One of the things I wanted the commission to think about was
election of officers.
That's something we need to do nominations in June and
my daughter's going into kindergarten in the fall so I'm gonna be less available than I've been.
So I really need staff support if I'm gonna stay on as chairman, if that's something the commission wants and the town wants.
If there's not an agent in place, I'm not I'm not going to raise my hand for that role.
And we also need more commissioners.
Unfortunately lost Rick recently,
we already had one vacancy. So his absence brings us to two.
And then
we do have Wayne Thorpe
serving as an alternate but he
hasn't been able to participate in meetings for quite some time now
and I think know Ed Smith has been upfront that his availability is somewhat restricted as well. So having
Commissioner Halsey service agent really further reduces our numbers.
So this has become a significant problem for wetlands.
>> And I think I'm realizing that with our small town it's
hard to recruit volunteers,
because there's
there are so many positions out there that we need help with,
so I think maybe just figuring out how we can get creative and reach out to more people.
Another thing to know is that Eric
and myself and Jim and Susan are having a meeting this Thursday to figure out how
the department as a whole
can work more
just effectively and efficiently. Everyone is working so hard,
and we appreciate Susan and Jim's time so much. But, you know, how can
I help? How can Eric help? How can we as a whole just make it more streamlined
and figure out
who's doing what
and.
Just make it better, because I think there's been so many changes
this past year
and staff
and
we appreciate
the Board of Selectmen approving more hours for the position because we know it's
really necessary. So I think that will help to attract
someone to the wetlands position.
And I'm not sure if Scott
is on, if he could,
I don't know,
if he has any ideas
for us as
a town to recruit more people to serve on wetlands. We also need
members for ZBA
as well.
>> Well, I'm just gonna tell you, Al right, I mean, as long as we're asking Jim to serve as our agent,
if either George, Jed or myself can't make a meeting, a meeting is gonna be canceled. And that's going to start to be a real problem when our applications start to pick up.
So it's going to be a problem for the town.
Jed stepped up to serve as P and C chairman is my understanding.
So I wouldn't be surprised if this availability is going to be at times more limited.
But this is a problem and it needs to be brought
to a higher priority than it's
>> happen to know of other people in town with interest
in this or experience?
>> Unknown There are other people in town with experience, I think Hank probably knows most of them.
But quite honestly, I don't feel it should be the responsibility of the commission to be knocking on doors. I think
the Board of Select may
>> on doors.
Just don't know who to knock
on.
How do we reach
people,
is a good question. I know we've been working on social media, a new website. We have our emergency alert, but,
you know, how do we personally reach out to people? I'm not sure if,
Scott or
Jeff McGuire, if you have any insight
or anyone that you may know that would be interested that
I could reach out to.
Are they on the line still? Scott, are you there by any chance?
Hang on.
There you are.
>> And Hank, I'm not sure if you're there right now either.
>> Yeah. I'm here. Any insight would be great. I know it's Yeah. We're having the same challenge with conservation commission. You know, I I I've approached some folks from that end that I haven't I've struck out with the Conservation Commission,
trying to get some folks engaged.
Yeah, you know, I don't know as many
I don't know anybody else with more wetland experience. Mean, there's Steve Fish, who was from ex DEP, who did a fair amount of time in various commissions in town, and I don't think he's interested. I know I'm on some boards with him. I know he's ratcheting back his time. He's involved with
One
that comes to mind is
Gordon Stratton, who used to be involved with the Lake Commission, I believe.
I
believe he's an engineer, but he
was pretty sharp with environmental
concerns and knew the town well. I don't know what his status is. Haven't talked with Gordie in many years now.
You know, he comes to mind. I don't know, Eric, do you know him? Is he around at all still?
Eric's on the call anymore.
>> I know Gordy
fairly well. He's a industrial hygienist.
So he's a good science background,
but travels a lot or he has.
I don't know whether he still is or not, whether he's still traveling.
>> I mean, and people with expertise are obviously great and phenomenal to have on the commission, but so are people with local knowledge. I think Rick Osborne was a great example of that. He didn't have a background
academically
in natural resources or anything like that, but he knew this town like the back of his hands and he could provide a lot of really helpful insight on applications.
I wouldn't want to discourage people to feeling like they can't volunteer for the commission because that's not their professional or academic background.
So just to put that out there. Good point. And would
you be able to send me
Gordon's contact info?
Boy, don't even know if I have it anymore.
I can get it to you.
Okay, thank you.
>> I would offer one other thought for the
board of selectmen to consider.
This is not typically,
something that's
thought to be favorable.
But a combined wetlands and conservation commission, I think in a town like ours where the population pool is so small,
it might make sense to look at what it would take to combine commissions and the pros and cons of doing so.
Because if neither commission is really being effective because it's shorthanded, then
maybe a joint commission would be more effective. I don't know. That would require ordinance changes and charter changes and things like that. That exists in other towns?
Yes.
There's a variety of models across the state.
This little history lesson, some of the
initial wetlands commissions were actually called conservation commission. So towns, sometimes their wetlands commission is their conservation commission.
Other towns like ourselves have two separate commissions.
And then other a third option is where well, sometimes have no conservation commission by law, you have to have a wetlands but not a conservation.
So I guess the fourth option would be towns have a joint conservation and wetlands commission,
which in I think a larger town, you know, like I work professionally with the town of Greenwich, they have two commissions, they're a huge town with you know, a lot of you know, huge applications,
it makes sense.
I think for the size of our town,
maybe that's something we should think about as a way to be more effective across the commissions. I don't know. It's a thought I'll put out there because I think we're at a point where we need to think outside the box. I think that's a very good idea, Megan.
>> George
Eliot here.
Regrettably,
any move to reconstitute
the commission would require a change in the charter,
which brings us to the same dilemma
as our former charter
revision committee
was unable reliably
to pull together a quorum
in order to get a hearing
or a valid meeting. And therefore, our last attempt at charter revision
went absolutely nowhere.
So
just saying here,
I think that it's
a good idea
and certainly worth looking at,
but it's more than something that simply having the Board of Selectmen look at it
would require. It would require a charter revision,
and that's a whole process in itself.
>> There might be a loophole. So the authority of wetlands comes from the state statutes
>> And It's in the state.
It's in the town charter.
There will be a conservation
commission. There will be
a
conservation commission.
>> I understand that. But what I was saying is the state wetland statute
authorizes the town to make their own commission by ordinance.
So there may be a poll
in the meantime. I don't know. I think it's worth talking to lawyers and exploring if the Conservation Commission would be amenable to it because
we're
not recruiting new people. I don't know where to find people. I mean, especially right now when we can't leave our houses, it's not the best time to be trying to recruit.
>> Fundamentally, we do have a human resource problem
for small tab
and trying to get people,
even though, I mean, I'm currently
on
the
committee to select
members for an advisory committee for the Andover Community Fund. In other words, we're trying to recruit people to give away money.
And even there, it's difficult.
>> Now if you recruit people to get money, I'm sure you'll have much more success.
>> Right, right.
But Megan, do think that that's something that we can pursue
is to coordinate the both of those commissions.
I think that's a very good idea and I'm going to look into it myself.
>> I think if you yeah even just kind of procedurally what it would take and then obviously just speaking for myself really not even for wetlands because we haven't had a chance to discuss this before tonight but
I don't you know what I'm blindside conservation if they're adamantly opposed to it
but I don't know of any other solutions at this point.
>> I think it's a good idea, Megan. I think the challenges though there are, you know, there's very different roles for a conservation commission and a wetland commission.
You know, so I think from the conservation commission standpoint, we would want to be
clear on the
planning aspect. What
the wetlands can't do is sort of the longer term conservation
planning,
which is what the Conservation Commission can do. So, So, I think we'd have to think. Now, there are other ways to get at that though. It doesn't necessarily have to come out of conservation
commission. So,
we'd need to think about that.
And I think you're right. We do have a challenge and it may make because of the size of the Taliban
and the pool of folks to get it may be a challenge to
really populate the two commissions separately.
>> I think would you because I don't know which towns offhand have joint commissions.
Would you be able to look into that at all so we could maybe ask them how they handle those challenges? Yeah, I'd be willing to do that. Know there are some. I know that, you know, that's a bit frowned upon.
>> You know, the Mackie Wickin folks, they started to really Yeah. Try to drive commissions to rather than having separate commission or rather than having a single commission to form separate commissions.
And a
large part of that, I think, was to try to get more
effective conservation planning versus just focused on site by site regulatory,
which I also I'm a big believer in. Have to do planning, you know, or you get behind the eight ball. But there are other ways to do the planning. It doesn't have to be through, as I mentioned, a conservation commission or a town's park.
It can be handled through the plan of conservation development through some committees and so forth.
Yeah, I can look at that. I know there are some that still, that have
combined commission, but it's not many.
But I'd be willing to look into that.
>> Thank you, Hank. And maybe, I think maybe we can connect offline too and brainstorm a bit.
Sure.
>> We just have to be careful about
being transparent government.
So let's
think about that with the connecting offline. That
was all I had for this evening. I don't know if anyone else needs your last chance before we entertain a motion to adjourn.
Okay, well, hearing no further discussion then I will entertain a motion to adjourn.
I move to adjourn.
Ten seconds.
>> All right.
I'll
do roll call vote. Vice Chairman Elliott, how do vote?
Yes.
>> Thank you. Commissioner Larson, how do vote? Aye.
Thank you. And Chairman La la I vote aye as well. So motion to adjourn at eight 51
three zero zero.
Thank you all for your time.
>> Bye.
Thanks for watching the show. Thank you all. Bye. Nice job.
Hello.